Charles Ruas Papers, 1924-2020: Finding Aid C1372
Manuscripts Division
- Photographs, 1924-2019; 3 boxes; 2 digital files
  - Alex Haley Portrait, 1976; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Author of Roots. Photo credit: Alex Gotfryd.
  - Michael Higgins Reading in Studio, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 14)
    Two photographs. Photo credit: Joan Schwartz.
  - Susan Howe and Taylor Mead, St. Mark's New Year's Eve Poetry Reading, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Two copies of a photograph. Photo credit: Joan Schwartz.
  - Susan Howe, Fanny Howe, and Family, 2019; 2 digital files; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 16)
    Photographs with Fanny Howe, Helen Howe, and Susan Howe taken by Rob Wynne (December 10, 2019) Light Industry, Brooklyn, for Mary Manning (their mother), Women Pioneers Project, Irish film director. Also of Fanny Howe, Helen Howe, and Susan Howe, with her daughter R.H. Quaytman. There are both physical and digital copies.
  - Joan Jonas and Rick Turner in Morocco, 1965; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 47)
    AM 2019-4
    Photo credit: Charles Ruas. Depicts Jonas with her brother sitting at a bar.
  - Joan Jonas, "Songdelay", 1973; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 16)
    Photo credit: Gwenn Thomas. Performers include Gordon Matta-Clark.
  - Joan Jonas in Studio by Jason Schmidt, undated; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 17)
    Two photographs signed by Jonas, taken for New York Times Magazine.
  - Tessa Kaner Reading in Studio, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Harry M. Koutoukas in "Turtles Don't Dream", 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 18)
    Two photographs by Joan Schwartz, along with some clippings about Koutoukas.
  - Les Lalannes, Les Meniers, Jean-Gabriel Mitterand on Château de Chenonceau Balcony, circa 1991; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 19)
    Snapshot by Rob Wynne, showing from left to right, Charles Ruas, Claude Lalanne, François-Xavier Lalanne, M. and Mme. Menier (the owners of the chateau), Jean-Gabriel Mitterand, and an unidentified couple on the balcony of the Château de Chenonceau.
  - Leo Lerman in Studio, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 20)
    Photo Credit: Joan Schwartz.
  - Michael Lesy, Real Life: Louisville in the Twenties, 1976; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 21)
    Promotional album page of photographs, Pantheon.
  - Mabou Mines, 1972-1974; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 22)
    Photograph of the original founders of the company. "The B-Beaver Animation," by Lee Breuer. Performers: David Warrilow, Ruth Maleczech, Frederic Neumann, Joanne Akalaitis, Dawn Gray. Paula Cooper Gallery 1972. MOMA 1974. Photo credit: Tina Girouard.
  - Taylor Mead Reading at St. Mark's New Year's Eve, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 23)
    Photo credit: Joan Schwartz.
  - Maureen Owen, Meredith Monk, Charles Ruas at St. Marks New Year's Eve Poetry Reading, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 24)
    Five photographs, including 1) Maureen Owen, (left) Meredith Monk (right), backstage; 2) Maureen Owen(left), Meredith Monk (middle), Charles Ruas(right); 3) Maureen Owen(left), Meredith Monk (middle), Charles Ruas(right); 4) Meredith Monk (left), Charles Ruas (right); 5) Meredith Monk (left), Charles Ruas (right). Photo credit: Joan Schwartz.
  - Marianne Moore Portraits, 1924-1981; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 25)
    Includes 1) Marianne Moore, promotional insert for The Complete Poems of…" Viking Press, 1981; 2) Marianne Moore in 1953, Photo Credit: George Platt-Lynes; 3) Marianne Moore in 1924, Photo Credit: Sarony.
  - Alice Neel Paintings, 1972-1974; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 26)
    Photographs of paintings by Alice Neel, including 1) John Perrault, portrait, 1972. Photo credit: Tracy Boyd; and 2) Cindy Nemser and Chuck Nemser, nude portrait, 1974. Photo credit: Eric Pollitzer.
  - Pablo Neruda Portraits, undated; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 27)
    Portrait of Pablo Neruda (Photo credit: Jill Krementz) and photograph of portrait painted by Carlo Levi.
  - Michael Newman A.K.A.L.Q.(Also Known As Lenny Quantum) Performance, 1976; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 28)
    Photograph of split screen for performance of A.K.A.L.Q.( Also Known As Lenny Quantum) in studio at WBAI. Photo credit: Joan Schwartz.
  - Anais Nin in Recording Studio, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 29)
    Photograph of Anais Nin, seated in WBAI recording studio, with Rob Wynne, artist orchestrating reading. Hands on left, Charles Ruas director. Photo credit: Joan Schwartz.
  - Steve Post by Monroe Litman, 1974; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - "The Two Character Play" (Out Cry) Actors, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 30)
    Photographs of performers in a performance of the play by Tennessee Williams, including a portrait of Robert Stattel, and three portraits of Maryellen Flynn (full face portrait; blowing bubbles; and in costume). Photo credit: F. Laun Maurer.
  - Lou Reed at St. Mark's New Year's Eve Poetry Reading, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Raymond Roussel as a Child, Sitting on a Swan Boat, undated; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Charles Ruas Conversations with American Authors Cover, 1985; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Ed Sanders Promotional Portrait and Reading at Saint Mark's, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 33)
    Promotional portrait for "Tales of Beatnick Glory" (Photo credit: Jill Kremens), and photograph of Sanders reading at St. Mark's New Year's Eve Poetry Reading (Photo credit: Joan Schwartz).
  - Polaroid of Rose Schacht, undated; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 20)
    Poet and screenwriter.
  - Dutch Schultz Leaving Jail in Albany, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 34)
    Photograph of Dutch Schultz (left) leaving jail in Albany, N.Y., after posting a $75,000 bond prior to trial for tax evasion. For The Last Words of Dutch Schultz, by William S. Burroughs (1975).
  - Lore Segal Portrait, circa 1970s; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 35)
    Author of Lucinella. Photo credit: Maria Elena de la Iglesia.
  - Marian Seldes Reading Miss MacIntosh My Darling, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 36)
    Photograph of Seldes reading in the WBAI studio (Photo credit: Joan Schwartz).
  - Eleni Sikelianos at St. Mark's New Year's Eve Poetry Reading, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 46)
    "Child poet" (age 10). Photo credit: Joan Schwartz.
  - Patti Smith Portrait, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 37)
    Patti Smith portrait by Robert Mapplethorpe made for publicity distribution for her first record, distributed by Arista Records.
  - Tony Smith and Barnett Newman with Seton, Beatrice, and Kiki Smith, circa 1960-1965; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 48)
    Two photographs. One was taken by Barnett or Annalee Newman and shows Tony Smith in front of one of his sculptures; the other, taken by Annalee Newman, shows Barnett Newman with Smith's daughters, Seton, Beatrice, and Kiki Smith, in front of the same sculpture. Both are signed by Seton Smith.
  - Jane Lawrence by Seton Smith, undated; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Han Suyin Portrait, 1976; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 38)
    Author of "Wind in the tower" (1976). Photo credit: Rhoda Nathans.
  - Nadja Tesich and Charles Ruas in Venice, 1963; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 22)
    Photocopy of a photograph.
  - Anne Waldman in Studio Reading Poetry, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - Neil Welliver "Cedar Water Pool" Painting, 1976; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 41)
    Photograph of painting by Neil Welliver: "Cedar Water Pool," Fishbach Gallery.
  - Geoffrey Wolff for "Black Sun", 1976; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 42)
    Includes a portrait of Geoffrey Wolff, author of Black Sun (Photo credit: John Osgood), and a photograph of Harry Crosby and Caresse Crosby, the subjects of Black Sun.
  - Virginia Woolf Portrait, undated; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 43)
    For Portrait of a Marriage.
  - Rob Wynne Artwork, 1975; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 44)
    Two photographs of Wynne's "The Mask," drawings in negative and positive, black and white, Stable Gallery.
  - Marguerite Young by Rob Wynne, 1980; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 23)
    Depicts Young with her doll collection at home on Bleeker Street.
  - WBAI Audio-Experimental Theater Mock-up, circa 1974-1976; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 45)
    Gwenn Thomas photograph of Joan Jonas performance inserted into the radio. Designed by Jonathan Andrews.
- Translation and Writings, 1970s-2004; 3 boxes
  Consists of translations and other writings by Charles Ruas.
  - Translation of Death and the Labyrinth by Michel Foucault, 1983-1985; 5 folders (Box 11, Folder 1-5)
    Includes a rough draft of the initial translation and a copyedited galley.
  - "The Ile de Re", undated; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Reviews, Writings, and CVs, 1970s-1980s; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Translation of "Claudio Bravo, Architect of Light" by Ben Jelloun, 2004; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Catalog for Marlborough Gallery.
- Family Papers and Tianjin History Collection, 1860-1966; 1910-1946; 9 boxes
  This group of materials consists of photographic albums and individual photographs, postcards, travel diaries, and some supplemental material documenting the history of the Ruas family in Tianjin, China, and illustrates the history of Tianjin primarily between the years of 1910 and 1946. Several of the photograph albums were put together by Charles Ruas' grandfather and father who were French engineers in the early Chinese ship-building industry at Dagu (Taku) and the water supply system of Tianjin. The Manchu General Marshal Yin Chang was the father of Charles Ruas's mother, so there are also some rare Chinese photographs of the imperial family.
  Two albums show the beginning of the beginning of the Chinese shipbuilding industry in the early 20th century at the Taku shipyards and colonial life in Tianjin in the 1910s and 1920. They show the Brossard shipyard, images of several ships under construction and the conditions of workers at the shipyards, and the various other shipyards at Taku. Other photographs show important landmarks in the city. Two additional albums show colonial life in Tianjin from the 1920s to 1946. They show historical events such as the famine of 1920-1921, the flood of 1924, the inauguration of the International Bridge, the Japanese attack on Tianjin in 1937, the Japanese Blockade of 1939, the great flood of 1939, the liberation of Tianjin by United States Marines and the history of the Ruas family in Tianjin. Another album, originally belonging to an unidentified American soldier of the 15th United States Infantry which was based in Tianjin, has photographs dating from 1912 to 1940, and includes photographs of Marshall Zhang Zuolin in Tianjin, General William Conner and Prince Chun, father of emperor Pu Yi, with his entourage. Other photos show city life and religious ceremonies.
  There are also a small number of rare photographs of the Qing imperial family illustrating the early interaction of the Qing court with Westerners. These include for example a photograph of Emperor Pu Yi against a painted automobile prop, taken at the British Country Club in Tianjin as well as a collection of photographs from a collection of glass negatives by Shun Ling, brother of Princess Der Ling, that show landmarks in the Forbidden City. The collection also includes a photographic album entitled 皇室旧影 that shows members of the imperial family. The photographs in this album were likely also taken by Shun Ling.
  Spellings/transliterations on folder titles reflect those found on the materials or the inventory provided by the donor.
  - Military Album of an American Soldier, 1912-1938 (Box P-000155)
    Military album of an unknown American soldier who was a contemporary of Charles H. Ruas in Tientsin. This album was purchased through friends in the "Old China Hands" organizations.
    Includes photographs of the 15th United States Infantry Regiment stationed in Tianjin, travel photos, and photos of Tianjin 1912-1938, to be replaced from 1938 to the outbreak of War in 1940 by a contingent of Marines from the Embassy's military security guards based in Beijing. The album begins in the early 20th century. Some photos are dated, such as the 1924 flood of Tientsin.
    Includes photographs of Chang Tso Lin, his private automobile; Marshal Chang Tso Lin in Tientsin; General William Conner; Prince Chun, the Emperor Pu Yi's father, with his full entourage in Tientsin. According to Pu Yi he left Tientsin and returned to his house in Beijing after the Great Flood of 1939 (in his memoir From Emperor to Citizen). Unique photo of Prince Chun from this period.
    Supplemental material includes: International Newsreel photo, 15th Infantry pitching pup tents in the British military base, Tientsin, Nov 13, 1931 (caption pasted on reverse); US Army Headquarters photo, Tietsin, 1920. Online research material.
  - Charles E. H. Ruas, Album of Great Flood of 1939, 1920-1939 (Box P-000156)
    This album comprises photographs taken by Charles Ruas, his family, friends, and colleagues. The album records the following events in the history of the city of Tientsin: the famine of 1920-21; the flood of 1924; the inauguration of the International Bridge and the Jing Gang Bridge; the Japanese attack on Tientsin in 1937, the beginning of the second Sino Japanese war, including the bombing of Nankai University; the Japanese blockage of the French and British Concession 1939; the great flood of 1939; the memorial for the late Charles Ruas, who died as a result of working in the contaminated waters of the flood of 1939 and photos of Ruas's family; document of Ruas death certificate, death notice in Pekin and Tientsin Times, North China Star, and a tribute from the British Municipal Council Water Works Report on the 1939 Flood; the US Marine liberation of Tientsin; and the Ruas family return to France.
    All photos with the exception of the following were taken by Ruas, family, friends, and colleagues: The second Sino Japanese war, 1937 photographs are from the Bristol University Archives, concentrating on the bombing of Nankai University. The blockage of 1939 photos are original press photos.
    Supplemental material includes original photos from newspaper archives of the period include: 1. International News Photos, Jul 30, 1939 "Livestock arriving for blockaded British Concession"; 2. ACME, 7/6/39 "Japanese Bottle up Food Supples Mean for British Tientsin"; 3. ACME, 6/28/30 "Typical Barricade of British Concession in Tientsin"; 4. Planet News Ltd, June 14th 1939 "Japan Begins Blockade of British Concession at Tientsin"; 5. A.B. Text and Bilder 7/31/1937 "Japanska Trupper I Tientsin"; 6. ACME Newspictures, Inc. 10/17/45 "Marines Occupy Tientsin."
  - Album of Charles Edouard Henri Alexandre Ruas, Tientsin, China, 1918-1919 (Box P-000157)
    M. Ruas began 2 identical albums of the Brossard shipyard in Taku, one each for his son and daughter. This album was for his daughter, Rose Juliette Eulalie Ruas, born in Millau, France 1909, died Sept 1935 in Dakar, Senegal.
    This album is an official archive of the construction of a boat in the Brossard Shipyard. All photos in this album are numbered and dated, beginning with photo #107, 5/12/18 to #170, 8/5/19. It is followed by photos of river traffic from Taku to Tientsin.
    Includes: a panorama (2 parts, facing pages) of the Brossard Shipyard in Taku 1919, where the boat construction depicted took place; a panorama (continuous) showing multiple boats under construction in the shipyard, 1919; a panorama (continuous, folded) showing the various shipyards of Taku, 1919; a panorama (continuous, folded) of a boat under construction, 1919.
  - Album of Charles Edouard Henri Alexandre Ruas, Tientsin, China, 1918-1919 (Box P-000157)
    M. Ruas began 2 identical albums of the Brossard shipyard in Taku, one each for his son and daughter. This album was for his son, Charles Edouard Henri Ruas.
    This album is an official archive of the construction of a boat in the Brossard Shipyard. All photos in this album are numbered and dated, beginning with photo #107, 5/12/18 to #174, 8/5/19. The album continues with personal photographs of business and leisure of M. Ruas senior and his enterprises. It portrays colonial life and the scope of his activities. Included are several photos of local places in Tientsin that were researched. The album concludes with the opening of the International Bridge and Charles Ruas junior as a member of the French Concession municipal council.
  - Personal Album, Charles E. H. Ruas (1904-1940), 1921-1930s (Box P-000158)
    This personal album starts with a 1921 visit to Beijing's tourist sites, including the Observatory, the Palace, the Temple of Heaven, the Summer Palace, the Great Wall, and the Ming Tombs. Interspersed are photos of Mr. Ruas's acquaintances among the military stationed in Beijing, a visit to the Pei Ta Ho seaside resort, and Shang Hai Kwan. Other photos include family photos of Ruas senior and his sister Rose; the International Bridge and the Jingang Bridge, on which Ruas worked as a young engineer; and the Tientsin Native City Waterworks, where Ruas began as an inspector and later became acting head engineer in the mid 1930s.
  - Frank Leckell Photograph Albums, 1930s; 2 boxes (Box P-000159, Box P-000160)
    Four photograph albums belonging to an executive of the Northrop Aviation Company, likely Frank Leckell based on a steamship dinner card and guest list included in one of the albums. Primarily consists of travel photographs, but also includes images of Central Aircraft Manufacturing Company (CAMCO) in Hangzhou.
  - Photographic Booklet with Members of the Imperial Family 皇室旧影 Huang shi jiu ying, undated (Box B-001565, Folder 1)
    This photographic booklet shows members of the imperial family. The photos in were likely taken by Shun Ling, brother of Princess Der Ling of the Imperial family.
  - R. Eddy Mathews, Diary of Travels in China, 1916-1917 (Box B-001565, Folder 2)
    Consists of a diary of R. Eddy Mathews, a former journalist for the Christian Science Monitor, who traveled to Tianjin to work for the Dollar Steamship line. Includes photographs, clippings, and ephemera.
  - A. M. Dollar, Diary of Travels on a Dollar Steamship, 1902 (Box B-001565, Folder 3)
    Consists of a diary by A. M. Dollar with photographs and ephemera from the Dollar Steamship Company and the American College Club in Beijing partly printed by the Peking Gazette Press.
  - Photograph of Pu Yi or His Brother Taken at British Country Club Tientsin, circa 1920s-1930s; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 4)
  - Photograph of Pu Yi as a Young Man, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 5)
  - Press Photograph of Japanese Soldiers Manning the Blockade of the French and British Concessions in Tientsin, 1939; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 6)
  - Military Press Photograph of U.S. 15th Infantry Regiment Stationed in Tientsin, 1937; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 7)
  - Tientsin Photograph Postcards, circa 1890s-1910s; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 8)
    Includes: Tientsin 1903: postcard of two French children in Chinese costume; pre-1900: three postcards of the French bridge in Tientsin; pre-1900: postcard of the French market in Tientsin; Postcard of Zaghouan, Le Temple des Eaux; pre-1900: French consulate in Tientsin; Illustration of a bridge over the Tientsin Canal (the Grand Canal of China); Postcard of horse and cart; Postcard of men airing their songbirds; Postcard of Wan-Kuo Bridge, Tientsin.
  - Photograph Postcards, circa 1900s-1940s; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 9)
  - Imperial Railways of North China Train Service Information Pamphlet, 1911; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 10)
  - Historical Photographs, circa 1912-1919; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 11)
    Includes an album titled "Revolution in China," Verlag con Franz Scholz, Tientsin (1912?); 12 photographs of the proclamation of the republic in Beijing; Sun Yat Sen in Shanghai postcard; military encampment photo; the founding of Nankai University postcard (1919); and a photograph of Premier Cho En Lai as a student at Nankai University playing a female role in a student theater production.
    Content Warning
    The "Revolution in China" album contains photographs of dead bodies.
  - Photographs of Tientsin and Beijing, circa 1900; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 12)
  - Political Postcards, circa 1910s; 1 folder (Box B-001565, Folder 13)
    Related to Revolution (1912?) and Loie Fuller.
  - Photographs Documenting the Great Flood of 1939, 1 folder (Box B-001566, Folder 1)
  - Photocopies of Chinese Documentation of the Great Flood of 1939, 1 folder (Box B-001566, Folder 2)
  - Postcard Photographs of Tientsin and Beijing, circa 1910-1920; 1 folder (Box B-001566, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of the Summer Palace, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001566, Folder 4)
  - Small Photographs of Chinese Cities and Architecture, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001566, Folder 5)
  - Quotations from Chairman Mao Tse-Tung, 1966; 1 folder (Box B-001566, Folder 6)
    First edition book.
  - Photographs of St. Louis College of the Marist Brothers for Boys, Tientsin, 1940-1946; 1 folder (Box B-001566, Folder 7)
    Includes photographs showing the student body of St. Louis College in Tientsin during World War II. There are photographs of Charles Ruas's junior French section and his older brother Franklin Ruas's senior French section. There is also a two-part photograph of the whole faculty and student body of the French and English sections.
  - Photocopy of a Panoramic Photograph of the German Concession in Tientsin, undated; 1 folder (Box P-000161, Folder 1)
  - Photograph of Empress Dowager Ci Xi, undated; 1 folder (Box P-000161, Folder 2)
    Photograph made from original negative. Notation on the back: Photograph from the late Princess Der Ling's unique collection of glass negatives, taken by her brother Shun Ling.
  - Shun Ling Hand-painted Photograph of the Forbidden City: Great Wall, undated; 1 folder (Box P-000161, Folder 3)
  - Shun Ling Hand-painted Photograph of the Forbidden City: Pagoda, undated; 1 folder (Box P-000161, Folder 4)
  - Shun Ling Hand-painted Photograph of the Forbidden City: Moat, undated; 1 folder (Box P-000161, Folder 5)
  - Shun Ling Hand-painted Photograph of the Forbidden City: Hall, undated; 1 folder (Box P-000161, Folder 6)
  - Shun Ling Hand-painted Photograph of the Forbidden City: Pavilion, undated; 1 folder (Box P-000161, Folder 7)
  - Photocopy of a Photograph of St. Louis College Boxing Club for Students, circa 1940; 1 folder (Box P-000161, Folder 8)
    Includes Brother Aloysius and a parent volunteer coach.
  - Charles E. H. A. Ruas Photographs, circa 1910s; 1 folder (Box P-000161, Folder 9)
    Includes a photograph of Charles Ruas with FC municipal court figures and a group photograph of a night club award celebration.